[Music]
Jean, how are you? Uh Dan, great. So
great to be here and always happy to uh
share stories about Steve Yaggi with a
former uh someone that he's also
impacted as well. So that has been
absolutely I trust he was as interesting
back then as he was as he is today. He's
always been a character. I think I think
that hasn't changed. That's for sure.
That's awesome. Well, Jean, I'm really
excited to uh kind of sit back and and
uh see what you've got to share with us
and then I'll be back at the be back at
the end to chat a little bit more. But
uh let's uh take it away. Fantastic. Uh
thank you. Yes. Uh so uh I've had the
privilege of studying high performing
technology organizations since uh 1999.
And that was a journey that started back
when I was the uh CTO and founder of a
company called Tripar in the information
security space. And so our goal in these
studying these high performers, it was
it was those organizations that had the
best project due date performance in
development, the best operational
reliability and stability and ops as
well as the best posture of security and
compliance. And so we wanted to
understand how did those amazing
organizations make their good to great
transformation so we can understand how
other organizations could replicate
those amazing outcomes. And so as you
can imagine in a 26-y year journey there
were many surprises but by far the
biggest surprise was how it took me into
the middle of the DevOps movement uh
which uh was so it was so still remains
so urgent and important. I think the
last time that we've seen any industry
disrupted to the extent that all our
industries are being disrupted today uh
was likely in manufacturing in the 1980s
when the US auto industry was upended
with the entrance of uh Toyota into uh
the uh automotive marketplace. And so uh
I got to work on the DevOps handbook
with Patrick Dubois. Uh I worked on
something called the state of DevOps
research with Dr. Nicole Forsman and
just humble. And more recently I got to
uh hang out with Steve Yaggi and I who I
met uh last June and I cannot tell you
what a fun adventure uh that has been.
So, what I'd like to do in the next uh
25 minutes is share with you what I've
been up to lately, what Steve and I have
been working on uh together um and share
what uh Vibe Coding has to do with uh
DevOps and the Dora anomaly and really
describe what Vibe coding has done for
me. I had mentioned earlier I've never
had as much fun as I'm having today
because of what AI assisted coding can
enable. And so uh I've written a bunch
of books including uh the DevOps
handbook which I mentioned before the
Phoenix project uh uh the accelerate
book as well as wiring the winning
organization. Um and so we had mentioned
Steve and so many of you uh may know him
uh through his one of the most best
depictions of uh the great Amazon API
rearchitecture in the early 2000s where
they went from doing being able to do
hundreds of deployments per day in the
late 90s grinding to a halt where they
could only do tens of deployments per
year. most deployments didn't uh even
finish uh to later they were able to do
hundreds of thousands of deployments per
day uh by 2011. And so one of the best
depictions of this uh was uh this famous
memo uh that Steve Yagi described saying
how you know all teams must henceforth
communicate only through APIs uh that
they can only communicate uh through
these processes. no other form of inter
interprocess communications would be
allowed and anyone who doesn't do this
would be fired. And of course in in the
Yaggi style he said number seven is
obviously a joke because Yaggi doesn't
actually care whether you have a great
day or a bad day. Um, and so that uh
famous memo actually landed uh him on
the front page of the Wall Street
Journal because that was actually meant
to be posted privately on Google+ and uh
he accidentally set it to public and uh
resulting in a 2 am call with the uh
with the Google uh PR managers. Anyway,
so I met him in 2024 um because of the
work that he was doing in uh what he was
calling chat oriented programming and uh
as a result of our conversation he wrote
this article called the death of the
junior developer which was so utterly
interesting uh and really described kind
of what is happening to the workforce
what could be potentially happening he
later presented at uh the enterprise
technology leadership summit this is a
conference I've been running uh for the
last 11 years uh describing how coding
is changing reaching out from underneath
us and how organizations uh need to get
ready. And uh one of the things that we
uh found that we had in common was this
belief that uh uh the days of writing
code by hand are coming to an end. And
so some of you saw the talk um uh
earlier from
um uh Dick about uh uh he was the MVP
champion and this is uh this is Dr. Eric
Meyer. So he is uh was in charge of C
before that. He was part of Visual
Basic. uh he wrote the hack language uh
at Facebook Meta and uh he gave this
amazing talk uh sometime last year who
described how you know time is the most
important thing that we have as humans.
can be neither stored nor created. And
so if we can find ways to save time, we
have to take it. And uh he said that um
you know for so long we thought as
developers that we would be safe from
automation. But uh you know any sort of
analysis we're finding that code
generation is actually one of the things
that AI is best at. Um and if we are the
last generation of developers write code
by hand, uh let's have fun doing it. Uh
so both Steve and I loved uh this talk
and um you know Steve more than anyone I
know has uh really adopted uh vibe
coding into his daily work. He's now
writing 12,000 lines of high quality
code uh for production that's well
tested. He's spending $3 to $500 a day
on three to five instance of cloud code
or source graph amp. Um you know that's
how he's racking up these uh sort of
numbers.
And what's astonishing here is that you
know all of the practices uh that he's
using right all of us can use uh in our
own daily work uh to have more fun build
you be more ambitious about what we can
build do things faster and explore a
much larger option space and so what is
our definition of vibe coding it's
really anything besides typing in code
uh by hand so that's a very expansive
definition um and so vibe coding
obviously was uh uh coined by Dr. Andre
Capathy um you know not so long ago in
December uh and already they're talking
about at Google actually instead of
fixing code just pulling the slot
machine lever like we saw earlier today
right and just generating a new solution
when the cost of creation drops it it
makes uh brings into possibilities you
know ways of solving problems that just
simply did not exist before. um you know
the cloud code team they were recently
Boris and Katherine Woo um they were on
the latent space podcast and they
described how 80% of all code for cloud
code was actually written by cloud code
and they're citing a within enthropic uh
somewhere between a two to 10x increase
uh in productivity or at least uh
compression in terms of how much time is
required uh to do things using cloud
code versus writing it by hand.
So here's the value that we put into uh
the book that we're working on. Uh we
call it fafo uh faster. We can build
things that we want faster. We can be
more ambitious about the things that we
can build. Uh three is we can do them
alone. Uh in other words, we don't have
to rely on a team or worse yet a a team
of teams, right? Uh we reduce the cost
of coordination as well as this other
cost of like it's very difficult to read
other people's minds even with AI. So if
you can do things alone, right? uh that
creates a whole bunch of independence of
action that didn't exist before. Uh we
can also have so much more fun doing it.
We know that from decades of
benchmarking is that when we are more
productive and we have more fun that is
a magical combination. And then uh one
of the things that uh I will try to
convince you uh in this session is that
the highest value of all is to be able
to explore more options to have more
swings at bat to explore more of design
space uh because we can do things so
quickly and easily.
So uh just as a personal example in the
last uh uh six months I did my first
large scale statistical analysis in
Python. So for the last 20 plus years
I've used primarily SPSS which is uh you
know one of the uh the best uh the best
that 1970s technology could uh give us.
Uh and I did it in Google Collab. I did
it in Python, a language I've only
spent, you know, maybe a hundred hours
in my whole career using. Um, and it was
the first time again that I did things
that where I have just decades of muscle
memory doing SPSS. Uh, that was magical.
I resurrected a new data pipeline from
uh Twitter, uh, which Twitter broke in
2023. But in support of the book, I was
able to get that up and running through
if this then that. Um, and I can't help
but notice that anyone who figures this
out and posts a repo uh, who talks about
it has a repo taken down. So if you have
any advice on you know uh how one can
actually talk about that without uh some
sort of takedown notice I would love to
learn and uh I b I've fixed bugs and
tools uh that I haven't touched in uh
two years have been bothering me uh all
possible because of you know primarily
cloud code coding agents um like GitHub
copilot uh like source coding and so
forth uh and augment code so uh I also
wrote three iterations of a writer's
workbench uh so uh actually I haven't
mentioned right. So Steve and I were
working on this uh book called Vibe
Coding. It's coming out in fall uh and
uh in summer and fall uh and uh there
were three iterations of it. The first
one was just a JavaScript app to reduce
the amount of uh copy and pasting
required to sling these u you know copy
paste prompts and data from one tool to
another. Uh I wrote the second
generation was a uh Google Docs add-on
uh which I've never written before. I
wrote that in 3 hours uh inside of
Google Appcript and uh that was great.
Uh both Steve and I used it. Uh but it
was so slow. It would take somewhere
between 15 to 30 seconds to open up
files to copy things to clipboards. And
so uh I wrote a third iteration uh in a
terminal application sort of like cloud
code. And uh that has been amazing. And
so really the net effect like so many of
you um developers is that you know I
there are nights where I can't sleep
because of all the things that I want to
build. I'm having to force myself to put
down the keyboard uh and go to sleep so
you know I can have a a healthy life. Um
but it's so full of danger as you know
right AI generated code can quickly
become non-modular. They can create
these Eldrich horrors these uh
incomprehensible code bases that are
impossible to understand let alone
change. uh you can uh create simple
changes uh where AI builds upon uh
builds upon its own unreviewed code
creating tight tightly coupled systems
no matter how many guidelines you give
it. And then um you know we know that uh
teams working in complex tightly coupled
architectures um the literature has said
is that uh teams working in bad tightly
coupled code bases are nine times more
likely to be fired or quit right uh
those same things can uh happen when
we're working in AI generated systems uh
which can turn nicely modular code
quickly into a big ball of mud and
um uh we know that you know if you don't
have fast feedback back loops. Uh we
know that fast feedback loops are
important uh to get feedback on a work
in development. Uh but with AI coding,
with vibe coding, we need even faster
feedback loops, right? That uh because
as the um uh time to reduce as the time
to generate code goes down, our feedback
loops have to be ever much more tighter.
And we need that happening in our most
inner development loops, right? They're
measured in seconds uh not minutes. And
so uh I had mentioned this by coding
book. This is coming out uh in the fall
or summer or fall. And again, I have
learned so much uh working with uh Steve
on this book. And again, I've never had
so much fun uh as right now. So, um I'd
mentioned this writer's workbench that
we uh wrote to uh help with the draft
generation and critiquing process. Uh
what's remarkable is that uh we burned
70 million tokens in 30 days. Uh that's
3,000 LLM hours. Um and this was just
amazing when I was writing the preface
for the book uh for my uh section. I was
stunned to find uh out that you know the
first line of code was written only 30
days ago. So you know uh what happened
in 30 life moves fast uh in the AI
world. Uh we found that uh even in those
30 days uh we went through the whole
life cycle of software where it was
exhilarating and working. it turned into
a haunted codebase that was impossible
to change and uh I was able to resurrect
it, you know, uh to support this
production need of getting the book out.
But again, uh there is a very um
incredible orthogonal relationship
between uh say vibe coding and vibe
writing. Uh it essentially turns um the
it is like a slot machine, right? As we
saw in the vibe coding uh demo, right?
Is that you have such high upsides but
also infinite downsides. In the slot
machine, you can only lose the amount of
money that you put in. When it comes to
vine coding, uh you can actually the
slot machine can actually reach into
your pockets, into your bank accounts,
right? And destroy your code base, which
uh actually almost did happen to Steve
uh
before. So, uh there are so many
interesting problems that still need to
be solved, right? How do you gain
assurance of code functionality when
it's no longer you typing out by hand
and maybe even in languages that uh you
don't know very well? uh what do you do
when all the jobs we had when we start
our careers are going away? This is
actually what someone uh who is head of
dev platforms at a foundation AI lab
said right uh how do we get our own
organizations ready for this incredible
new technology and for that matter how
do we measure the value that genai
creates for
developers so uh let's move into the
second portion of the talk which is uh
you know about how we measure value and
so this is um one of the things I'm most
professionally proud of in my career is
working on the state of DevOps research
um I started this uh with Jez Humble in
2012 and uh uh Dr. Nicole Forsman joined
the team in 2013. And so this is a cross
population study uh that spanned over
60,000 respondents uh over six years. Um
and so the cross population instrument
is the same uh technique that they used
in uh the health uh profession right to
uh establish the link between smoking
and early morbidity and mortality. So we
use the same instrument to uh try to
find out what do high performers look
like and what are the things that
correlate or even predict performance.
And what we found for six years in a row
is that high performers exist and they
massively outperform the non- high
performing peers. And so um you know we
know that uh high performers deploy
multiple times a day. So that's two
orders of magnitude uh faster than the
peers. But more importantly they can
deploy in one hour or less. In other
words, how quickly can we go from code
committed into version control into
integration through testing through
deployment. So customers saying thank
you. Again, that's two orders of
magnitude faster than the peers. Uh
what's remarkable is they're getting far
better outcomes. Uh when they do a
deployment, they're seven times more
likely to succeed without causing a sean
outage, a service impairment, a security
breach, or a compliance failure. And
when something bad does happen, uh which
Murphy's law guarantees, they are able
to fix things in one hour or less.
That's three orders of magnitude uh
faster than the peers. And so what we
know now uh from six plus years of
research is that the only way that you
can get these small uh you know these
amazing reliability profiles is to do
smaller deployments more frequently. And
so uh we know that uh over the years you
know uh these high performers because
they're integrating information security
objectives into everyone's daily work
they are spending only one half the
amount of time remediating security
issues. And in addition to these great
uh technology measures, they are twice
as likely to exceed profitability,
market share, and productivity goals uh
or twice as likely to achieve
organizational mission goals regardless
of how they choose to define it. And so
it just shows that you know uh when
technology uh when mission achievement
requires work that we do in the
technology value stream, DevOps helps
with the achievement uh of those goals.
So um what we know uh from the
enterprise technology leadership summit
the devops enterprise summit is that
this is not just for the uh big tech
companies this is across every uh
industry vertical um across um uh
whether it's profit or not profit and um
you know we know this is true in
pharmaceuticals uh so this is from fizer
describing how they're elevating the
productivity of thousands of developers
across all the parts of fiser whether
it's research and development uh
pharmaceutical development uh sales and
marketing um Vanguard uh is an
organization has 9.5 trillion dollars of
assets under management 10,000 plus
developers and seammens uh they give us
an amazing experience report showing
that how uh they are applying the same
techniques for computer tomography um
inside for a fleet of thousands of uh CT
scanners inside of hospitals and by
doing that they were able to reduce the
time to get software into the
certification ation process. They could
do it every day uh versus spending up to
six months to get software ready for
certification. So always being
certification ready. So are we there yet
with Vibe coding? Uh no. In fact, one of
the case studies we put into the vibe
coding book was uh a friend of ours Luke
Burton who was at Apple and now Nvidia
describing how uh he had written
firmware uploading software for his CNC
machines. So those are the metal
grinding machines. And uh had he not
been paying attention, it would have
actually required a factory reset of a
machine that's hundreds of pounds
requiring access to the uh the factory
uh panel. Um so just showing how so much
vigilance is required. And so um yeah,
just to show how uh potentially
dangerous uh AI is, there was something
that uh really peculiar that showed up
in the Dora report. Uh so this is uh the
DevOps research and assessment
organization that was the uh the state
of DevOps research was acquired by
Google cloud and they found this
astonishing finding uh that said the
more AI you use the worse throughput got
and the worse stability got when I read
these findings I it was just uh uh
astonishing right in fact I got in
contact with them and uh yeah and the
reason is that it just does not square
with my own experience where I feel like
I am 10, 20, 30 times more productive
with AI assist than without, right? What
could explain, you know, this anomaly?
And scientific anomalies are often the
source of the most significant
breakthroughs, including Mercury's orbit
uh revealing this true nature of
gravity, uh the uh eclipse in 1919, uh
validating Einstein's discoveries. So
our goal is to um we're resembling a
dream team of researchers uh where our
goal is to see if we can explain the
anomaly, right? And actually be able to
tease out what value um you know we can
actually get from JAI. Um so here's two
hints. Uh this is Fernando Cornago. He
is global SVP of digital tech and Adidas
and he described a 700 person pilot that
they used internally. And one of the
great um uh piece of evidence that he
was able to show was that um it requires
uh loosely coupled architectures. It
requires fast feedback loops and when
you do this you can get a 50% increase
in happy time. So this is a time that uh
uh developers uh they appreciate.
They're working on things that advance
their craft that help advance uh the
mission goals. Right? unhappy or
annoying time, right, is you know
dealing with brittle tests or dealing
with environment issues or uh dealing
with uh uh you know impossible to
understand test failures. And so uh he's
describing that they can uh they're
finding like a 30% reduction in uh poll
request times. Uh and so you know we
know there's something there right and
that architecture and fast feedback
loops uh are discriminant. Uh Bruno
Pasos uh this is Bruno Pasos. He is head
of dev platforms at uh Booking.com. they
have uh 3,000 developers and uh one of
the things that they found um in their
year-long plus pilot uh is that they're
observing 30% reductions of merge
request times just like Adidas and also
uh 70% reduction in diff sizes and so uh
we know that the smaller diffs the
faster we can approve them for whatever
reasons right developers being
disciplined about using uh vibe coding
techniques they're also u putting in
merge requests that are smaller and
easier to prove So more research needed
there and this is really what we're
hoping to uh tease out uh in uh this
study of Gen AI and developers. So let
me share with you uh what excites me so
much about uh vibe coding which is what
we're calling fafo be able to do things
faster be more ambitious what we can
build be build be able to do things
alone have more fun doing it and have
more swings of bat. So
um what's interesting to me is that um
you know clearly I can do things faster.
In fact I was able to uh in my first
pair programming session with Steve Yagi
I was able to write a program that took
these excerpts I generated from
screenshots of YouTube videos and turn
them into video excerpts I could post on
YouTube which is actually how I first
met uh Dr. Eric Meyer. It was my first
interaction with him was commenting on
his video. I did that in 42 minutes. Um,
and so my my uh reflections on that is
that one, it was faster, but two, it
enabled me to do things that were more
ambitious. In other words, that video
excerpt creator was something I've
always thought about. I had wanted to
build something like that for years, but
um I always slotted that as a next month
activity. And maybe it was because the
perceived benefit wasn't high enough. Or
maybe the difficulty made the juice not
worth the squeeze. Or maybe there was
some other opportunity with a higher
more immediate payoff that I chose to do
that instead of writing the video extra
creator. So these are all economic
decisions about how I chose to spend my
time. That's actually not how my brain
works. But economics give us a great way
of talking about how we why we do things
one thing versus another. And so the
fact that I could be more ambitious
about what I could be build and do it in
less than an hour, not days or weeks,
just opens up worlds of possibilities in
terms of what we can do. In fact, a
cloud code team described that one of
the things they've noticed is that a lot
of pull requests, they never make it to
the backlog. They're just done uh in
that hour just because it's easier to
just do it then than it is to deal with
all the bookkeeping uh you know and
putting the backlog where it may never
ever get done. So allows uh the
combination of ambitious and faster is
very very
powerful. Um the third dimension is do
able to do things uh yourself. So Steve
uh told me this story last year that I
found very impactful. He was talking to
his then head of AI who showed him a
multi-class prediction model that he had
trained and deployed in a single day
with the help of a coding assistant.
What's really remarkable about that
story is that had that happened the year
prior in 2023, that would have been a
six-w weekek university senior level
intern project. So, um it was great for
the head of AI to be able to do it uh
himself. Maybe not so great for that uh
junior uh developer who lost an
opportunity to do something amazing. But
it just shows how doing things alone
allows us to uh reduce the cost of two
very important taxes. One is
coordination cost, right? every time you
have to work with another person or
another team, you have to deal with
synchronization, coordination,
prioritization, uh reporting, uh all
these things and that's not free. The
second one is that whenever you're
working with someone else, uh you just
can't read someone else's mind, right?
And so being able to lower uh that cost
of um uh not avoid that altogether by
doing things yourself, right, has
tremendous value. Um four, we can have
more fun doing the work. Without a
doubt, my personal experience is that
using vibe coding techniques, I having
so much fun. Uh so it's a very addictive
um uh thing, vibe coding, right? Is that
you have intermittent rewards like a
slot machine, right? And that's actually
the most addictive pattern that causes
addictive behaviors. Um and so I think
this is why so many people are saying um
you know, I'm up till 2 am, right?
Because it's uh it's just so fun. The
last thing I want to share with you uh
is explore more options. Um, and I want
to share with you. So, this means having
more swings at bat, research more
alternatives, prototype more ideas,
analyze more risks to avoid going
through uh one-way doors that you can't
get back through uh if you uh choose the
wrong door. And so, this is all what
happens when uh we can lower uh the cost
of experiments and this makes it easier
to expand the frontier of what you can
build. And so, um there are three key
ideas in economics. One is a time value
of money. Meaning a dollar now is more
than a dollar tomorrow. Two is portfolio
diversification, right? Uh whenever
don't put all your eggs in one basket.
And the third is option theory. The more
uncertainty you have, the more valuable
it becomes to defer a decision. In other
words, defer the decision uh when until
you have more data. And so when things
are as uncertain as now, uh you don't
want to get into long-term commitments.
You don't want to get into a three-year
outsourcing contract, right? because you
know everything can change next month or
even tomorrow and so uh Steve Yaggi is
the person on the lower right uh Steve
Dr. Steve Spear is on the upper left and
the person who is a pioneer in
modularity and option value and
modularity is Dr. Carlos Baldwin and we
uh got a master class in understanding
how to identify option value, how to
measure it and it comes down to this
incredible formula called NK divided by
T and sigma. And so we all know the
value of modularity and the feel like
option value tells us why. N is the
number of modules that can be worked on
independently. K is the number of
parallel experiments that can be run on
each module. T is the uh time required
to actually perform an experiment. And
sigma describes uh the riskreward uh
uncertainty. And so
um when sigma is one, you basically you
know everything ahead of time, right?
You don't need option values, you don't
need experiments, right? Because you
always know what the right answer is.
When sigma is infinite like right now,
right? Option value is very very high.
And so we want the most number of
modules that we're work on
independently. We want to perform the
most number of experiments. And we want
to spend the least amount of time
performing experiments. And so this is a
scalar value uh that if we can increase
modularity, increase number of
experiments, decrease the amount of time
required, right? Uh this creates
exponential value um in terms of the
option space that you can explore. So
think of the slot machine, right? You
want to find the slot machine that's
paying out the highest uh right and you
want to defer your decision until you
know which slot machine uh is paying out
the highest. So
um uh so yes the the time has never been
better to be a developer. So let me
leave you uh with this um you know I am
so eager to find out how leaders are
using this amazing new technology to
help their organizations win. Bruno
Pasos from Booking.com. He'll be
presenting at the conference I'm running
uh in September uh in Las Vegas. Uh so
will Fernando Cornado uh the VP the SVP
of uh digital Adidas. Uh we're hoping to
get some of the other amazing case
studies of how people are really driving
the frontier of performance. And so uh
if you are interested in that, please
join us in September. The help I'm
looking for is anyone who can share
experience reports about how they are
using AI to generate uh amazing
solutions and help your organizations
win. Please contact me. Uh, if you're
interested in anything I've written,
including excerpts from the vibe coding
book, just send an email to Jean uh,
real jeene kim sendyouslies.com subject
line. Let's do DevOps. I think uh, I'm
not sure if uh, the Jennai one took um,
just send me that uh, email and you will
get an automated response in a matter of
minutes. So uh, uh, I thank you so much
for your time and I look forward to your
questions.
Okay, thank you so much, Jean. That was
really fun. Uh, it seems like you uh you
got across the the fun that you're
having uh in this new world. Oh my
goodness. Like I said, I've never
learned as much as I have uh right now
and I've never been having much fun uh
in terms of like not just coding, but
all the research around like what does
it take to create the conditions so that
people can actually get value out of
this new amazing technology. Yeah,
totally. It it resonated a lot. I feel
like I can dive into areas that I've not
like you were talking about getting into
Python. I've had the same thing. The
whole T-shaped developer, right? Like
it's totally changed what we're able to
go into and and uh and just have
confidence in going into which is really
fun. I was talking to a developer who,
you know, their company has a monor repo
where before it' be like here's the Rust
developers and they live within this
part of the source pool here, right? And
then now they're diving into each
other's code and uh they they still need
the expertise, right? They're still
getting reviews from the people that
really understand it and so you get into
this kind of virtuous learning loop
which is which is really fun. Um it
absolutely what a time to be alive,
right? Totally. Okay, I want to pull up
a question here. Um we often talk about
the time you've like writing the code so
to speak. Uh but Patrick was curious how
much time you spent reviewing compared
to you know the actual code generation.
Oh my gosh. Oh that uh what a great
question Patrick. So yeah so for um
Yaggi to post these numbers like 12,000
lines of uh code committed uh he's
reviewing a 100,000 lines of code and in
fact he's obviously not generating any
of the code. So all his time is spent
reviewing. And so this is for a uh
multi-million uh line code base called
WBurn. It's this game that he wrote 35
years ago. And it's something he knows
intimately and so often when we were in
our bookw writing sessions right that
he's watching you know uh the output of
you know three at back then it was only
three coding agents but it just shows
that um you I think the u what we need
to get good at is review uh I had
mentioned uh you know burning 70 million
tokens uh while writing the book um and
uh to write three paragraphs um like uh
you know Patrick when we worked together
on the DevOps handbook so much of it was
interview and then uh one of us would
take the lead at generating the first
draft, right? Uh, you know, to be able
to put in a transcript and say target
um, you know, uh, three to five
paragraphs, right? And, uh, go from one
model to 10 models to 50 models
simultaneously, you're expanding the
option space, right? You're actually
increasing K uh, and decreasing T,
right? Which actually allows you to find
that lightning in a bottle. So, uh, we
would review 30 to 50 pages, right, to
cobble together three to five
paragraphs. So, it just shows how time
goes from generation into reviewing and
selection. That's I think it just shows
the thing that becomes most important is
like judgment and taste and knowing what
you want. Uh
yeah, that makes sense. You're talking
about the workbench. Um and you know,
you're adding all of this code really
really quickly. How do you find the
process kind of scaling over time? And
you mentioned just then that Steve Yagi
with Wven like he has the whole codebase
in his head so he can be the reviewer
and the like like how are you finding
things as as it's scaling and the
individual human maybe doesn't have the
entire codebase within their head even
quicker with it went great until it
didn't. I remember uh uh there was one
point in time where I needed to um
paralyze the ranking function, right? I
was trying to decrease t um and I looked
inside the code. It was this uh 3500
line function right where I didn't even
understand how the output files were
being generated. I didn't understand the
function signature. I spent 20 minutes
trying to understand it and uh then
forgot it because it was just so
incomprehensible to me. It took me two
and a half days uh during a writing
deadline to um uh actually Steve had to
uh he had a medical emergency uh and so
I use that time to actually fix the code
um and so that's what it took to
resurrect the codebase into something
that could change again. And so it just
shows that
um for any given solution, for any given
solution, there are an infinite ways to
solve it. And AI will find the most
alien ways to solve it if you if you're
not careful. And so uh uh I think um I
thought I learned my lesson and uh I
actually tried to build something like a
Java swing UI and I just found that uh
uh the AI would just find any way to put
pixels on that screen. like no no you're
only allowed these four functions to get
things onto the screen. Uh and it just
takes that level of uh vigilance
otherwise uh you know you have a lot of
cleanup to do and when you're building
when you're relying on the functionality
uh it's a nightmare to try to recreate
it anyway. So uh I think any developer
will resonate with that story. Totally.
No, that makes so much sense. And then
you you you had on your slide talking
about you know test-driven development.
Uh what was that process like? because
we were chatting earlier with someone
about kind of the chicken and the egg of
oh developers really don't like writing
tests so can the AI write the tests and
oh there's all these tests so can the AI
take the tests and write the code yeah I
think right I mean uh what is it like
all um tests are specifications but not
all specifications are tests and in my
opinion I think it's crazy absolutely
crazy not to write the test first uh
because at that point you now have
specification, but you have something
that is testable. Um, and uh yeah, right
because it it it concretizes your
interface. You're testing uh the outputs
of that interface, right? And you're
forcing the AI to stay in that box. I
mean, uh that is uh that solves so many
problems in my experience, right? Uh uh
that that goes so far in terms of like
preventing the you wake up and you are
see a room full of AI generated horrors.
Yeah. No, totally. And you're talking
about how with the swing example for,
you know, how it found alien ways just
to put pixels on the on the screen.
Yeah. And I see that all the time with
tests, too, where if you don't write
really good tests, it'll find lots of
ways to kind of get around to make that
test pass. Oh, yeah.
Ones of deleting code and putting pass
in there and the like. Yeah. In fact,
there's one learn that we put into the
book which is uh like there's something
that you have to be so vigilant about is
uh the fact that AIs are bad at
instruction following, right? That's
well known. But uh the fact that um you
know essentially AI are really good at
hijacking the reward function. And so
when you say like make these 10 tests
pass, right? It might do a great job on
the first six or seven, but as it's
running out of output context, right, it
will just it will often say, all right,
I did uh I made all the tests pass, but
just disabled the last three or you know
uh uh because uh it wants to be helpful.
So those are things I think all these
things suggest we really want to work on
small tasks. Uh there was a great line
from uh one of the other sessions that
said, you know, target your output
generations to be about 100 lines of
code long. I don't know if that's the
right number but yeah it's probably
close to 100 than a thousand right and
so right uh another reason to sort of
shrink uh the ambition of the tasks yeah
makes sense okay got another question
here for you so what strategies have you
found work for avoiding cascading design
problems and what are some formats with
vibe coding that you have found
effective yeah I think uh like one of
the things that we know from the state
of DevOps research is that architecture
is one of the top predictors of
performance you know meaning that um you
know My my recent understanding of this
is that it really is about having
independence of action. You want pieces
uh that can work independently of each
other at the same time without any
ability to interfere with each other.
And u I would say most of the vibe
coding disasters that I've had uh are
where you'd have two pieces that were
once separate somehow get stuck together
again, right? And uh you know I I think
um anything where you can sort of signal
to the AI, right? whether it's in the
claude MD file in something right it's
like work only on the files that I give
you right don't uh don't back door
yourself into another module uh that's
um I think that's how you prevent the
cascading part of design problem um and
I think the other uh thing that sounds
so obvious but you know every every
project every endeavor you can decompose
into a task tree or task graph just
thinking through what that is right and
decomposing it and then sort of starting
at the leaf nodes, right? That's where
um I still catch myself making errors
where I do that generate a plan and then
I have it do too much when I really I
should just be sticking to the leaf
nodes um because it's easier to verify
uh it's easier to validate as you go um
and it's uh easier to spot when it's
coloring outside the lines. Yeah, makes
sense. Awesome. Thank you so much, Jean.
That was that was great information.
look forward to reading the new book and
uh thank you again for taking the time
to to join us today. Very good. Well, if
you're interested in free excerpts, just
uh send an email to that
sendyouslies.com and I look forward to
hearing from you all. Thank you.
Awesome. Thank you.